Guide to the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Graphic Arts Collection, 1803-1988 RL.11023
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina graphic arts collection
1803-1988 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina
RL.11023
3 Linear Feet
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) graphic arts collection is an artificial collection of engravings, etchings, lithographs, screen prints, drawings, and sketches with themes related to Jewish religion, history, and culture. Artists represented include William Henry Bartlett, Paul Bourguignon, Gustave Doré, Joseph Margulies, Cécile Reims-Deux, and Yehudit Yelin-Ginat. The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) is an independent organization dedicated to preserving and presenting the history of the Jewish people of North Carolina.
Historical note
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) is an independent organization dedicated to preserving and presenting the history of the Jewish people of North Carolina. Through public programming and exhibits, the JHFNC aspires to educate and showcase the richness of Jewish Life as well as promote a familiarity with the culture and lifestyle of Jews to the general public. In 2014, the JHFNC transferred their historical collections, including the materials in the graphic arts collection, to the Rubenstein Library.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged alphabetically by last name of the primary artist. Works by unidentified artists appear at the end of the collection and are listed alphabetically by title.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Related Materials
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) graphic arts collection is an artificial collection of engravings, etchings, lithographs, screen prints, drawings, and sketches with themes related to Jewish religion, history, and culture. Plates removed from eighteenth- and nineteenth-century encyclopedias, Bibles, travel literature, atlases, and other illustrated volumes make up approximately two-thirds of the collection. The remainder of the collection contains twentieth-century prints and drawings, including original prints by Jewish and Israeli artists.
Artists represented in the collection include William Henry Bartlett, Paul Bourguignon, Gustave Doré, Joseph Margulies, Cécile Reims-Deux, and Yehudit Yelin-Ginat.
Provenance
The materials in this collection were received as a gift as part of the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in June, 2014.
Palestine -- Pictorial works; Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina; Bartlett, W. H., William Henry, 1809-1854; Bourguignon, Paul, 1906-; Doré, Gustave, 1832-1883; Margulies, Joseph, 1896-1983; Reims, Cécile; Yelin-Ginat, Yehudit
- Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina graphic arts collection, 1803-1989 and undated; 1
  - Lake of Tiberias, or Sea of Galilee = Lac de Tibériade, ou Mer de Galilée, 1847; Steel engraving (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Allom, Thomas; Floyd, W.
  - Cesarea, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    A version of this engraving appears in editions of "The Christian in Palestine, or, Scenes of sacred history: historical and descriptive" by Henry Stebbing
    Bartlett, William Henry; Cousen, Charles
  - Enclosure of the Temple, Jerusalem, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Bentley, Joseph Clayton; Bartlett, William Henry
  - Façade of the Tombs of the Kings, Jerusalem, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Challis, Ebenezer
  - Halt above the north end of the Dead Sea, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Armytage, James Charles
  - The Hill of Samara, 1847?; Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Publication information printed below image: London: Geo. Virtue. A version of this engraving appears in editions of "The Christian in Palestine, or, Scenes of sacred history: historical and descriptive" by Henry Stebbing
  - The Lake of Tiberias, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Bentley, Joseph Clayton
  - Mount Gerizim and the Vale of Nablous (from Mount Ebal), Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Wallis, Robert; Bartlett, William Henry
  - Mount of Olives from the wall, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Brandard, Edward Paxman
  - Nazareth, looking towards the Plain of Esdraelon, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Wallis, Robert
  - Plain Er-Rahah--Mt. Sinai. Mt. Mennacia Convent. Peak Sussafeh. Mt. St. Catherine., 1847?; Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Cousen, John
  - Pool of Siloam, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The River Jordan (Greek bathing place), Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Cousen, Charles; Bartlett, William Henry
  - Sidon and Mount Lebanon from the sea, 1847?; Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Publication information accompanying image: London: Geo. Virtue. A version of this engraving appears in editions of "The Christian in Palestine, or, Scenes of sacred history: historical and descriptive" by Henry Stebbing
    Bartlett, William Henry; Fisher, Samuel
  - Tiberias, Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Bartlett, William Henry; Brandard, Robert
  - Valley of Sichem and Nablous. Cerizim. Nablous. Ebal., Steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mont Sinaï - Couvent de Ste. Catherine., circa 1840-1880; Line engraving (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Blanchard, Auguste Thomas Marie
  - Jewish woman with her veil and rich ornaments, mentioned in Isaiah 3d.16.17--25., [1730 or later]; Copper engraving (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Text accompanying image: P. 54. Vol. III. T. A version of this engraving appears in English-language editions of Calmet's "Dictionary of the Holy Bible"
    Bleyswyck, François van
  - Melchizedek, circa 1955-1988; Color ink sketch, sheet 28 x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bourguignon, Paul
  - Pencil sketch of a man, circa 1955-1988; Pencil sketch, sheet 28 x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Witch of Endor, circa 1955-1988; Color ink sketch, sheet 28 x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Moysés hace brotar agua de la roca, circa 1871-1888; Wood engraving (Box 2, Folder 4)
    A version of this engraving appears in editions of Félix Torres Amat (translator), "La Sagrada Biblia" (Montaner y Simón, publisher)
    Doré, Gustave; Trichon, François Auguste; Monvoisin, Gaston
  - Isaac recibe á Rebeca, circa 1871-1888; Wood engraving (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Trichon, François Auguste; Monvoisin, Gaston; Doré, Gustave
  - Ein Judenmächen und ein jüdischer Kaufmann aus Algier. (Costume Bild)., 1853?; Hand-colored steel engraving (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Text accompanying image: Bild zur Theaterzeitung No. 19.
    Geiger, Andreas
  - [Leah], 1989; Cut-paper work with calligraphy; sheet 41 x 41 cm (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Goodman, Galia
  - Never again, Aquatint (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Print numbering: 36/60
    Koock, Klara
  - Contemplation, 1966?; Etching; sheet 345 x 327 mm, plate 225 x 185 mm (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Print numbering: 120?/243. sheet 325 x 345mm; plate 225 x 185 mm. Includes title and artist's signature in pencil
    Margulies, Joseph
  - Jüdin aus Sinope., 1887?; Hand-colored wood engraving (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Text accompanying image: Blätter für Kostümkunde. Neue Folge. 169. Blatt.
    Mücke, Heinrich Carl Anton; Henkel, R.
  - The Jewish feast of Purim or Lots. In 1712., circa 1850-1858; Transfer lithograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publication information accompanying image: A Fullarton & Co., London & Edinburgh. A version of this print appears in "The faiths of the world: an account of all religions and religious sects, their doctrines, rites, ceremonies, and customs," v. 2
    Forrest, William; Picart, R.
  - Ancient Palestine, 1854?; map with illustrations; hand-colored steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Text accompanying image: "The Illustrations by H. Warren & Engraved by J. B. Allen; The Map Drawn & Engraved by J. Rapkin." Publication information accompanying image: The London Printing and Publishing Company. Versions of this map appear in editions of "Tallis's illustrated atlas and modern history of the world."
    Rapkin, J.; Warren, Henry; Allen, James Baylis
  - Modern Palestine, 1854?; map with illustrations; hand-colored steel engraving (Box 2, Folder 5)
    "The Illustrations by H. Warren & Engraved by R. Baker; The Map Drawn & Engraved by J. Rapkin." The London Printing and Publishing Company. Plates likely removed from an edition of "Tallis's illustrated atlas and modern history of the world."
    Rapkin, J.; Warren, Henry; Baker, R.
  - [Psaumes] CXXXI, 1951; Etching; sheet 320 x 452 mm, folded to 320 x 226 mm, plate 206 x 238 mm (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Folded leaf with plate and text in French and Hebrew. Forms part of: Cecile Reims, Psaumes (Paris: Editions Arts du Monde, 1951)
    Reims-Deux, Cécile
  - [Psaumes] CXL, 1951; Etching; sheet 320 x 452 mm, folded to 320 x 226 mm, plate 177 x 246 mm (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The gallant behaviour of Sir Sydney Smith at the siege of Acre., 1803 March 19; Copper engraving (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Richter; Hawkins
  - Passover plate, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    numbering on back: 1
    Scherr, Mary Ann
  - Hannukah menorah, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 24 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    numbering on back: 2
  - Ram's horn, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    numbering on back: 3
  - Torah, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 20 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    numbering on back: 4
  - Candlesticks, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    numbering on back: 5
  - Kiddush cup, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 20 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    numbering on back: 6
  - The Ark, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    numbering on back: 7
  - Eternal light, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Talis/Yarmulke, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    numbering on front: 9
  - Mezuzah, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    numbering on back: 10
  - Talis, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yarmulke, 1974; Ink drawing, sheet 24 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hebron, circa 1830-1870; Steel engraving (Box 1, Folder 12)
    "Drawn...from a sketch by Lieut. Col. McNiven." Publication information printed below image: "Blackie & Son, Glasgow, Edinburgh & London"
    Selous, Henry Courtney; McNiven, Thomas William Ogilvie; Bradshaw, S.
  - Israel's Declaration of Independence, circa 1959; Photomechanical color print; sheet 41 x 54 cm (Box 3, Folder 4)
    "Presented on the 11th Independence Day by Maariv Daily and American Israeli Paper Mills Ltd." Publication information also printed in Hebrew.
    Szyk, Arthur
  - [Declaration of Independence for the State of Israel], after 1948; photomechanical color print on cardboard mount; mount 49 x 60 cm, visible image 36 x 48 cm (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Tel Aviv, 20th century; Watercolor on foam core mount, mount 12 x 36 cm8.5 x 14 in, mounted on foam board (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Sirrah
  - De kerk in het Nederl. Israel. Oude Mannen- en Vrouwen Huis; Het Nederl. Israel. Ziekenhuis uit den tuin. Bl. 63., 1845?; Lithograph (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Vries, R. de, Jr. (Ruurt de)
  - untitled, circa 1950-2003; Color screen print, image 22 x 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Signed in pencil by artist and numbered: 127/300.
    Yelin-Ginat, Yehudit
  - untitled, circa 1950-2003; Color screen print, image 22 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Signed in pencil by artist and numbered: 120/300.
  - untitled, circa 1950-2003; Color screen print, image 22 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Signed in pencil by artist and numbered: 122/300.
  - Unidentified artist - Austria - plate 32 ("A Polish Jewess"), 1813; Hand-colored aquatint (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The plate was likely removed from an edition of William Alexander, "Picturesque representations of the dress and manners of the Austrians." A clipping of the original text accompanying the plate is attached.
  - Unidentified artist - Autriche. Juifs polonais, 19th century; Hand-colored aquatint (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Text accomanying image: Pl. 13
  - Unidentified artist - Marchand juif á Constantinople, Hand-colored intaglio print (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Text accompanying image: [plate] 52. Pag. 211. Tom. 2
  - Unidentified artist - Passover observances, 1870 September 1; Transfer lithograph (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Engraving signed by artist and initialed by engraver? The image is printed on page 736 of Sunday Magazine, Sept. 1, 1870.
  - Unidentified artist - Roman monuments of Judea vanquished., Transfer lithograph (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Text accompanying images: "Judea capta", "Arch of Titus". The plate was likely removed from an an edition of "Fragments, being illustrations of the manners, incidents, and phraseology, of the Holy Scriptures…with additional remarks, observations, and plates, intended as a continued appendix to Calmet's Dictonary of the Holy Bible..."
  - Unidentified artist - Der Sinai., [between 1828 and 1874]; Steel engraving (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Text accompanying image: CCVI
  - Unidentified artist - Temple de Iupiter Hammon, Line engraving (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Writing at the center of the image, possibly the artist's signature: G. Sch[ai?]tte[n?].
  - Painting in Israel: 15 reproductions in colour, 1955; 4 pages, 14 leaves of color plates (Box 1, Folder 23)
    P. Abramovic, "Drying Nets (Tiberian)"; M. Castel, "Sephardic Synagogue in Safad"; J. Eisensher, "Street in Old Safad"; Errell, "Mother and Child"; A. L. Fein, "Beth-Alfa"; J. Frenkel, "Old Safad'; M. Janco, "Smoking the Waterpipe"; Kahana, "Oriental Composition"; J. Kossonogi, "Street in Tiberias"; M. Levanon, "Jerusalem"; Mokady, "Boy With Stick"; A. Naton, "Shabbat Candles"; J. Saritzky, "Tel-Aviv"; J. Simon, "Earth"; E. Sigard, "Road to Zikhron Yaakov"